Eric Fisher Wood Papers
Eric Fisher Wood Papers
1909-1964
Wood, Eric Fisher, 1889-1962.
8.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American army officer, architect, author, founding member of the American Legion. Correspondence, diaries, speeches, training manuals, published materials by and about Wood, military records, reports, maps, and photographs pertaining mostly to Wood's military service. Also, correspondence and research material relating to Leonard Wood.
148763
Biographical History
Eric Fisher Wood (1889-1962) was an American engineer, military officer (retiring with the rank of Brigadier General), and co-founder of the American Legion.
Born in New York City in 1889, Wood was educated in private schools and at Yale. He graduated in 1910 with a B.A. degree in economics and English and a PhD in Civil Engineering. He did post-graduate work at Columbia and at l'Ecole des Beaux Arts in Paris. While there, he was enlisted by the American Embassy to help care for the flood of problems brought on by World War I. He served as an attaché and kept a journal which he later published as a book. Wood then enlisted in the British and French armies, winning many decorations. When America entered the war, he enlisted as a private and rose to the rank of colonel. He fought in France, and, remaining there after the war, was one of the four original founders of the American Legion (1919) and served as an officer for many years. Returning to the United States, he made architecture his career, in Pittsburgh, Pa., and became one of the nation's leading architects. He served as a National Guard Commander in Pennsylvania. At the start of World War II, he was recalled to service, serving all through the war, eventually rising to brigadier general. His oldest son, Eric Jr., was killed in action in 1944. After the war, Wood returned home and became active again, as he had before, in Pennsylvania state politics, strongly supporting the Republican party, and serving as an advisor to Nixon and Eisenhower. Wood died in 1962, leaving his wife, whom he had married in 1918, and his three surviving children.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eric Fisher Wood Papers include correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, diaries, and published material.
Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing. Correspondence to and from others is also arranged chronologically.
Subject files consists of material on a variety of topics. The three largest subjects are the American Legion, World War I, and World War II.
American Legion material includes bulletins, a charter, correspondence, a history, American Legion magazines and newspapers, reports, speeches, and other material pertaining to the American Legion.
World War I material includes articles by Wood, photographs of Camp Sherman, correspondence, material on the 83rd and 88th Divisions, French publications, manuscripts of Wood's British service and notes on his war service.
World War II material includes clippings, correspondence, maps, notes, a manuscript by Wood, and material on German concentration camps and prisoners-of-war and displaced persons.
Other topics represented include Georgia, the National Guard, Pennsylvania state politics and Gen. Leonard Wood. The series also contains illustrations of Wood's architecture, a diary, scrapbooks, and material on such notable military figures as Winston Churchill, Gen. Douglas MacArthur, and Gen. George S. Patton.
Manuscripts consists of manuscripts of articles, books, columns, newspaper articles, notes, reports, speeches, and similar items by Wood.
Published material includes circulars, lectures by Wood, magazines, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, press releases by Wood, a program, reports, and speeches. The articles, clippings, pamphlets and speeches are either by Wood, about Wood or his works, or by and about others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondenc is arranged alphabetically by sender, and outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by type and ends with manuscripts of others. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type, and further arranged chronologically where necessary.
Related Material
See also the
Eric Fisher Wood Family Photographs
.
Separated Material
A 1915 copy of Wood's memoirs, Note-book of an Attaché, has been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Military history; Wood, Eric Fisher, 1889-1962.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.; American Legion.; United States. -- Army.; United States. -- Army -- Officers.; Architects -- United States.; Authors, American.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; United States -- History, Military -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Maps (documents); Photographs.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Architects.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Eric F. Wood, 1967.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1914; 1915,; 1917,; 1924,; 1954,; 1959,; 1960,; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1919; 1922,; 1924,; 1946,; 1953-1954,; 1959,; 1961,; 1962 (Box 1)
  - To and from others, 1917; 1964,; undated (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - American Legion
    - Bill and patent, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
    - Bulletins, 1919; 1921-1922 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, meetings, minutes and resolutions, 1919; 1935,; 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Calls for Conventions, 1919; 1921,; 1959; 1919 (Box 1)
    - Charter (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1916; 1919,; 1921,; 1934,; 1938-1940,; 1950,; 1952-1954,; 1958-1959,; undated (Box 1)
    - Drafts and notes, undated (Box 1)
    - History, 1919; undated (Box 1)
    - Lists, 1919; 1921,; 1958-1959,; undated (Box 1)
    - Magazines
      - 1919 (Box 1)
      - American Legion Magazine, Mar 1939 (Box 1)
      - American Legion Weekly, 1919 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda, 1919 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper, Stars and Stripes, 1919 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1919; undated (Box 2)
    - Pamphlets, 1920; 1952-1953,; undated (Box 2)
    - Proceedings, 1919-1921; 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Published material, 1921; 1952,; undated; miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Report of National Emblem Committee, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1919; 1959 (Box 2)
    - Speeches, 1919; 1920,; undated (Box 2)
    - Universal Military Training, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Architect engineer questionnaire, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Architecture, 1929; undated; illustrations of Wood's work; photos and published material (Box 2)
  - Book reviews, 1915; typescripy copies (Box 2)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1955; undated; notes, published material (Box 2)
  - "Diary While at the Ecole des Beaux Arts in Paris", 1913; 2 folders, 438pp (Box 3)
  - Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, the Command and General Staff School, 1936-1937; 1939 (Box 3)
  - Georgia
    - Correspondence, 1942; 1943 (Box 3)
    - Notes, 1941-1942; 1944,; undated (Box 3)
    - State Guard, 1942-1943; undated; correspondence (Box 3)
    - State Guard, manuscripts and published material (Box 3)
  - Gettysburg (Civil War) notes and maps, undated (Box 3)
  - Itinerary of speaking trip, undated (Box 3)
  - List of Wood's architectural projects, undated (Box 3)
  - MacArthur, General Douglas, 1934; 1951,; 1961,; undated (Box 3)
  - Martin, General Edward, 1938-1939; 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Memorial to Eric Wood, Jr., 1953; undated (Box 3)
  - Meyerode, Belgium, statements concerning son's WWII service and death (Box 3)
  - National Guard
    - Analysis, directives, proposals and speeches, 1931-1932; 1941,; 1943,; undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1921; 1936-1937,; 1939-1940 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933; 1937,; 1939-1941 (Box 3)
    - Notes, 1927-1928; 1931,; undated (Box 3)
    - TLX Training, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Training memoranda, 1925; 1927,; 1930-1932,; 1936 (Box 4)
  - Pennsylvania state politics
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - List, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Memos and notes, 1962; undated (Box 4)
    - Published material, 1962; undated (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - 1962 (Box 4)
      - Complete report, 1952-1960; 2 copies (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1927 (Box 4)
    - Whalley, J. Irving (Representative), undated; biography (Box 4)
  - Patton, General George S., 1945; 1947,; 1955 (Box 4)
  - Personal Army papers, 1918; 1923,; 1932,; 1938-1942,; 1946,; 1949 (Box 4)
  - Plattsburg, New York military training camp, 1916-1917; photos and roster (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1915; clippings; 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Shannon (Ireland) Free Airport, 1960; 1961,; 1962,; undated (Box 5)
  - Telephone bill, 1964 (Box 5)
  - World War I
    - Army General Staff Courses, 1918; undated (Box 6)
    - Army General Staff College maps, undated (Box 6)
    - Army Memoranda, 1918; 1919,; undated (Box 6)
    - Article on British censorship by Wood, 1917; published material (Box 6)
    - Awards and certificates, 1915; 1918-1919,; undated (Box 6)
    - "The Battle of the Marne", undated; manuscript (Box 6)
    - Camp Sherman
      - Correspondence, 1917-1918; 1919,; 1922,; 1928,; undated (Box 6)
      - Chapter I, Personalities, August 1917-June 1918; undated; photos (Box 6)
      - Chapter II, first training event - exhibition of bayonet fighting, undated; photos (Box 6)
      - Chapter III, first half of September, 1917; photos (Box 6)
      - Chapter IV, 2nd half of September, 1917; photos (Box 6)
      - Chapter V, October and November training, 1917; photos (Box 7)
      - Chapter VII, Tactical Training December, 1917; photos (Box 7)
      - Chapter VIII, Maneuvers January-March, 1918; photos (Box 7)
      - Chapter IX, Station personnel and installations, undated; photos (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1915-1919 (Box 7)
    - Data, 1914; 1916,; 1917,; undated; published material (Box 7)
    - Documents, 1914 (Box 7)
    - 83rd Division
      - Correspondence and manuscripts, 1917-1918; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Camp Sherman, 1917-1919; undated; manuscripts and published material (Box 7)
    - 88th Division
      - 1918-1919, undated (Box 8)
      - Camp Dodger, 1917; 1919; published material (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1918-1919; 1922,; undated (Box 8)
      - Memoranda, 1918-1919 (Box 8)
      - Published material, 1917; 1919,; undated (Box 8)
    - Flag incident, 1916-1916; undated (Box 8)
    - French publications, 1915; 1916,; undated; includes article about Wood (Box 8)
    - Lists, undated (Box 8)
    - Lusitania, 1915-1916; undated (Box 8)
    - Manuscripts of British Service, 1916-1917; undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "The New Army Act and the Militia" by Wood, undated; published material (Box 9)
    - Notes, 1918; undated (Box 9)
    - Notes and maps, 1914; undated (Box 9)
    - Notes from France, 1918; undated (Box 9)
    - Notes on British Service, 1916; 1917; manuscripts (Box 9)
    - Notes on British Service, 1914; 1917,; undated; published material (Box 9)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 9)
    - Photographs, 1919; undated (Box 9)
    - Platoon composition and formations, undated (Box 9)
    - Postal censorship, 1916-1917; undated; published material and photos (Box 10)
    - Preparedness, 1914-1916; undated (Box 10)
    - Press statements, 1916; undated (Box 10)
    - Service with the British, 1917; undated; photos (Box 10)
    - Staff College, 88th Division
      - Correspondence and published material, 1918 (Box 10)
      - Manuscripts, 1918 (Box 10)
    - Villa incident, Mexico, 1915-1916; undated (Box 10)
  - World War II
    - Abstracts of Interrogation, undated (Box 10)
    - Clippings re World War II after VJ Day, 1940; 1941,; 1944-1947,; undated (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1945; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Documents, 1944-1945; undated (Box 10)
    - "An Examination of the Campaign in Normandy" by Wood, 1940; manuscript (Box 10)
    - Exercise, 107th F.H. Regimental Staff School, "The Battle of Rossignol, August 1914", 1939 (Box 10)
    - Extra photographs and negatives (Box 11)
    - German concentration camps, 1945; published material and photos (Box 11)
    - Maps of France and Germany, undated (Box 11)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1942-1946; undated (Box 11)
    - Notes, miscellaneous, 1941; 1944-1945 (Box 11)
    - P.O.W. and D.P. Division, 1944-1947; 1950,; undated (Box 11)
    - Souvenirs, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
  - Wood, General Leonard
    - Correspondence, 1919; 1923,; 1926-1928 (Box 11)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1920-1927 (Box 11)
    - Photographs, 1917; undated (Box 11)
    - Typescript of conversation, undated
  - "Woodrow Wilson and Mexico", 1916; correspondence, article, photos (Box 11)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles
    - "An Armed Democracy, An Organized Nation", undated (Box 12)
    - "Bank Architecture", 1921 (Box 12)
    - "The Battle of Arras", undated (Box 12)
    - "The Battle of Chicago", undated (Box 12)
    - "The British General Service Medal for WWI", undated (Box 12)
    - "Colonel L'Hospital", 1940; 1960-1961,; undated; with photos (Box 12)
    - "The Grizzly and the Brown Bear", undated (Box 12)
    - "The Luckiest Morning", undated (Box 12)
    - "Necessity for Military Discipline", undated (Box 12)
    - "The Writing on the Wall", undated (Box 12)
    - Unidentified articles, 1922; undated (Box 12)
  - Books
    - The Big Game of Alaska, undated; first carbon (Box 12)
    - Notebook of an Attaché
      - Original notes, May-Nov 1914; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Original notes, Dec 1914-Feb 1915 (Box 13)
      - Original notebooks, 1914; undated (Box 13)
  - Columns, "To My Neighbors", 1940 (Box 13)
  - Data notebook "commenced at 1925-1930 Encampment", undated (Box 13)
  - Memoranda, 1961; undated (Box 13)
  - Newspaper articles, 1914; 1940 (Box 13)
  - Notes on "Times" article, 1916 (Box 13)
  - Notes, "What the F.A. can do for the Inf. Limitations of F.A.", undated (Box 13)
  - "Notes of E.F.W.'s Visit to Alaska, 1909"
    - Holograph, partial (Box 13)
    - Revised typescript pp. 1-73 (Box 13)
    - Typescript pp. 1-44 (Box 13)
    - Revised Typescript pp. 74-124 and extra pages (Box 14)
  - Reports, 1917; undated (Box 14)
  - Research materials, 1951; undated (Box 14)
  - Scenario by Wood, untitled, undated (Box 14)
  - Speeches, 1916-1917; 1920-1921,; 1924-1925,; 1929-1931,; 1938,; 1941,; 1943,; 1946-1947,; 1951,; 1956,; undated; 6 folders (Box 14)
  - Manuscripts of others, 1921; undated (Box 14)
- Published material
  - Book, The Notebook of an Attaché (The Century Co.: New York), 1915
    Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging, Nov 2009.
  - Circulars, undated (Box 15)
  - Lectures by Wood, 1943 (Box 15)
  - Magazines
    - Intelligence Digest, 1949 (Box 15)
    - Progress, 1928 (Box 15)
  - Magazine articles
    - By Wood, 1915; 1930,; undated (Box 15)
    - About Wood, 1915; undated (Box 15)
    - By and about others, 1915; 1926-1927,; 1932,; 1934-1936,; 1941,; 1951-1952,; 1955-1956,; 1958,; undated (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - By Wood, 1916; undated (Box 15)
    - By Wood, "To My Neighbors", Feb-Dec 1940; Feb-May 1941; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - About Wood, 1915-1918; 1920,; 1933,; 1947,; undated (Box 16)
    - About Notebook of an Attaché, 1915; 1916,; undated (Box 16)
    - About Notebook of an Intelligence Officer, 1918; undated (Box 16)
    - About The Writing on the Wall, 1915; 1916,; undated (Box 16)
    - By and about others, 1915; 1918,; 1921-1923,; 1925,; 1927,; 1928,; 1934-1936,; 1938,; 1940,; 1951-1952,; 1955-1957,; 1959,; undated; 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Pamphlets
    - About Wood, undated (Box 16)
    - By and about others, 1917; 1926,; 1928,; 1933,; 1948 (Box 16)
    - By and about others (Army), 1917; undated (Box 16)
  - Press releases by Wood, 1916 (Box 16)
  - Program, 1916 (Box 16)
  - Reports, 1917; 1939 (Box 16)
  - Speeches
    - By Wood, 1940 (Box 16)
    - By others, 1955; 1956 (Box 16)